Guide to the Campaign for Peace and Democracy Records TAM.462
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Campaign for Peace and Democracy Records
1968-1998
1981-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Campaign for Peace and Democracy
Landy, Joanne
TAM.462
19 Linear Feet in 19 record cartons
The Campaign for Peace and Democracy (founded in 1982 as Campaign for Peace and Democracy/East and West) is dedicated to advancing a progressive and non-militaristic U.S. foreign policy -- one that encourages democracy and social justice by promoting solidarity with activists and progressive movements throughout the world. The records contain correspondence (principal correspondent is CPD founder and longtime head Joanne Landy), minutes, reports and other internal documents, political activities files, research files, printed ephemera from CPD and other organizations, Joanne Landy's personal notebooks,research materials, government documents and documents created by various Non Governmental Organizations (NGOs).
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Joanne Landry on behalf of the Campaign for Peace and Democracy in 2008; additional materials were donated in 2016. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2008.046 and 2017.014.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Campaign for Peace and Democracy (founded in 1982 as Campaign for Peace and Democracy/East and West) is dedicated to advancing a progressive and non-militaristic U.S. foreign policy -- one that encourages democracy and social justice by promoting solidarity with activists and progressive movements throughout the world. The Campaign opposed the Cold War by calling for "detente from below," engaging Western peace activists in the defense of the rights of democratic dissidents in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, and enlisted East-bloc human rights activists against U.S. policies in countries like Nicaragua and Chile. Along with the European Nuclear Disarmament Movement, the Campaign built grassroots solidarity across the Cold War divide, and refused to "choose sides" in the East-West conflict.
Scope and Content Note
The Coalition for Peace and Democracy Records (dated 1968-1998) contain correspondence minutes, reports and other internal documents, political activities files, research files, and printed ephemera from the Coalition for Peace and Democracy (CPD) and other organizations. Correspondence primarily relates to the work of CPD founder and head Joanne Landy. The collection also contains Landy's personal notebooks, research materials for an application for a MacArthur Foundation writing grant for a project titled "The Role of Western Economic Policy in the Transformation of Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union", and documents created by various Non -Governmental Organizations (NGOs). Audio visual materials in this collection include two boxes of cassette tapes and VHS recordings of CPD board meetings, lectures, forums, and conferences in the late 1980s and early 1990s. Recordings feature discussions on topics on trade, United States economic power, and Europe after the fall of the Soviet Union. They also include some recordings of programs from WBAI Radio on similar topics.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Europe, Eastern -- Foreign Relations -- Soviet Union.; Soviet Union -- Foreign Relations -- Europe, Eastern.; Soviet Union -- Politics and government.; Notebooks; Research (document genres).; Correspondence.; Anti-globalization movement.; United States -- Foreign relations.; Human rights -- Europe, Eastern.; Nuclear disarmament.; Antinuclear movement.; Human rights.; Peace movements -- United States.; Campaign for Peace and Democracy; Campaign for Peace and Democracy/East and West; Landy, Joanne
- Records, c.1980-1983; Peace and Democracy News, 1984-1995 (name changed to Peace and Democracy in 1994). Note: Campaign for Peace and Democracy East and West was founded in 1982, and became Campaign for Peace and Democracy in 1990. Some material is from predecessor organizations., circa 1980-1995 (Box 1)
- Records, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
- Records, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
- CPD director Joanne Landy's research materials for MacArthur Foundation writing award "The Role of Western Economic Policy in tehe Transformation of Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union" (Part 1), 1990-1991 (Box 4)
- CPD director Joanne Landy's research materials for MacArthur Foundation writing award "The Role of Western Economic Policy in tehe Transformation of Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union" (Part 2), 1990-1991 (Box 5)
- Records, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
- Records, 1994-1996 (Box 7)
- Special Topics (Polish Solidarnosc, Independent Soviet Peace Group, Czechoslovakia's Charter 77 Group), circa 1985, undated (Box 8)
- Joanne Landy's personal notebooks, miscellaneous records and printed ephemera, photographs, 1968-1975 (Box 9)
- Balance sheets and receipts, 1992-1993 (Box 10)
- Receipts, etc., 1991 (Box 11)
- Miscellaneous records and printed ephemera, 1988-1991 (Box 12)
- Chronological Correspondence Notebooks: 1, 1988-c.1991 (Box 13)
- Chronological Correspondence Notebooks: 2, 1984-1998 (Box 14)
- Chronological Correspondence Notebooks: 3, 1988-1992 (Box 15)
- Chronological Correspondence Notebooks: 4, 1986-1992 (Box 16)
- Individuals: donors and others, c.1986-1994 (Box 17)
- Board Meeting and Public Event Recordings (Box 18, Box 19)
- Archived Website, Jul 8, 2009-ongoing
  Scope and Content Note
  The Campaign for Peace and Democracy, founded in 1982, works to advance a progressive and non-militaristic U.S. foreign policy and is opposition to current U.S. foreign policy. Orginally, the campaign engaged Western peace activists in the defense of the rights of democratic dissidents in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe, and enlisted East-bloc human rights activists against anti-democratic U.S. policies in countries like Nicaragua and Chile. The majority of the Campaign's work has been its efforts to work with dissidents and social justice movements worldwide, and to forge alliances between them and progressive movements in the United States. The website contains petitions, endorsements, action alerts, news analysis, and endorsements.